[Music]
hello and welcome to episode 13 of the
inventory tutorial series and episode
two of the shop system so we've got our
shop system here you can see that we've
got this kind of pop-up window that's
there going to be our shop and you see
that it's going to be able to have a buy
and sell tab so this is going to show
either the shop inventory or the player
inventory we're going to add things to
this window here which is the shopping
cart and then we'll be able to buy the
items or sell our items that'll be
coming in the next video in this video
which will be working on laying all this
out getting it all set up and making a
few scripts and just you know laying the
groundwork to actually plug in the ui to
the
shop system we made in the previous
video and you can see currently if we
hit play we can walk over to our npcs
which we've made and we can interact
with them and it'll bring up the window
that's what we're going to get to in
this video it's not the most exciting
thing but it's a necessary step on the
way to displaying our shops so let's
just jump straight into it okay so let's
get started so let's go on our canvas
here i'm gonna make a new um empty i'm
gonna call this the shop ui controller
and to this i'm going to make a panel so
right click ui and i'm going to put in
the uh graphic that i've been um using
for the other inventory stuff um panel
it's not there
what's it called so with that panel i'm
just going to make it a kind of
brownie color you know you put any sort
of graphics in here that you want so
i'll make it this color here and i'm
going to get the panel and
let's go into sort of 2d ui mode
gonna be doing a lot of ui stuff let's
zoom out and we can make this panel nice
and big uh you can make it fill the
screen if you want and if you want the
shop to kind of fill up the whole screen
but i'm just going to make it like this
so it'll pop up like this and then i'm
going to make a new um empty i'm just
going to call this uh window left
because we're going to split our shop
window into two
sections and i'm also going to make a
empty
say window to our panel object we're
going to add in a
horizontal layout group and we're going
to let this we're going to let this
control the child size and we're going
to say the child alignment is going to
be the upper center now if we go over to
our window left you can see that the box
is now uh half of the panel that we've
made and the other box is on the other
half of the panel that we've made so to
our window left object i'm going to
create two
ui buttons um and if you've got all of
these weird lines up you can remove
visualize i'm just going to bring this
up here let's make it a bit uh bigger
and this will be the by tab so we'll
click this and it'll show us the items
that we can buy from the shop and then
we can click we're going to make a sell
button which will show us uh the items
in our inventory and this like and allow
us to sell them to the shop so we've got
our buy button uh let's rename this just
so we know exactly what it is buy button
and then we'll uh ctrl d duplicate this
will be the uh cell button move this
over and then swap this text to say cell
and then underneath our buttons um we're
going to make a ui um scroll view i'm
just going to drag this just above the
buttons in the hierarchy and we're going
to select a
stretch to fill the whole um the whole
canvas but then we'll just bring it down
and to not kind of overlap the tabs i
don't want the horizontal bar on our
scroll rex so i'm just going to uncheck
horizontal and we can remove the
horizontal scroll bar we'll just select
none and under scroll view we can just
delete the horizontal scroll bar and
then if we go to the vertical scroll bar
we can just drag that out so it fits our
entire panel then i'm going to twirl out
that and i'm just gonna rename this
content um object to um item list just
so we know kind of um i'm gonna rename
this to item scroll list just so we know
um
if we're just looking at this that this
is the scroll lift and then we need to
just make this a bit bigger um just kind
of just below the scroll bar you can see
depending on how big this is that's kind
of responsible for how much we can
scroll um so we'll we'll have to change
and tweak this probably as we go but for
now that's fine then over on the right
hand side so let's just close that on
the right hand side i'm going to make a
um another empty we're going to call
this
item preview and can make this fill this
side of the screen take it all the way
to the top and to our item preview we're
going to add
a sprite so ui
image and we'll call this the item
sprite and let's just drop in a sprite
just so we can see how this is all
looking so we'll do our bottle and we'll
do preserve aspect and let's just make
this a little bit bigger we're going to
add some text so we can say ui text mesh
pro bring this down we'll auto size it
we'll align it um horizontally and
vertically and here we'll just say uh
health ocean again just so we can lay
this all out this will be all changed
through code anyway um and then let's so
we'll rename this to item this item name
then we'll let's just duplicate it we'll
move it down this time i'm gonna make
this a little bit bigger there i'm gonna
left align it and top align it and say
this is the description and we'll make
the max size just a little bit smaller
and then we'll rename the object to item
description and then we're going to make
another object we'll right click
create empty and this is gonna be the
shopping cart so this is gonna have uh
another scroll view so we'll right click
ui scroll view and then let's drag this
um down so we'll position that kind of
down here again we'll make it fill the
this half of the canvas so we'll just
drag that out and like before we don't
want a horizontal one and we can get rid
of the horizontal bar the um vertical
scroll bar fill the actual frame and it
says missing let's just select none um
on there got our scroll list here and
then again let's rename the content
panel just so we know exactly what this
is so this is going to be the um thing
art list and then to our shopping cart
item let's create a button so we'll say
uh ui button text mesh pro and this will
be the um buy sell button and we'll just
drag this down here just under our
shopping cart let's make it a bit bigger
we'll go to our text and we'll say um
buy items so we're gonna make some more
text so we're gonna right click shopping
cart ui text text mesh pro let's bring
this down here uh we can make it bigger
kind of to here and i'm going to center
and right align this i'm just going to
put in
total uh 5 000 gold that's how much our
shopping cart this is going to display
how much our shopping cart is worth so
we can rename this object to basket
total and then i'm going to duplicate
this and let's move it up and this is
going to be um shop gold so this is how
much gold the shop has access to so
let's say uh
a thousand and i'm just going to make
this a little bit smaller this is the
sharp gold and then let's duplicate this
again move it over um we need to left
align this rename it to player goal oh
what's going on rename this to play
layer gold and then in the text we can
say player gold and we'll say 500 g so
this is how our shop is going to look
and it's going to have um items kind of
added to it into this scroll view here
and let's get a look for what that's
going to look like so if we go up to our
um window left scroll view let's go to
our uh item scroll list and let's create
an empty and call this um shop item list
ui so to this we're going to add in a
item sprite so we'll say ui image let's
call this uh item sprite and again just
for simplicity let's put our
item in it and i'm going to make this
the size of our panel here so we've got
our item sprite we're going to add some
text to this so we'll say ui text mesh
pro left align it i'm going to center it
though and we'll say health ocean that
out to about there you can position this
kind of where we want it this is going
to be item name we'll duplicate this
move it down this will be the item
amount so this is going to be how many
of the item the shop has so we'll say
it's got five potions i'm just gonna
make this a little bit smaller than the
text and the name of the text and then
i'm gonna add two more buttons to this
and then that should hopefully be most
of the ui done and we'll just need to
start the kind of code side of it so
let's do button text mesh pro i'm going
to say add to
cart button i'm going to make this a
square and for the text i'm just going
to put a plus symbol this a bit bigger
so it's going to be to add it to the
cart and we can drag that over and then
let's duplicate this move it over we'll
call this the remove from cart button
and instead of a plus it can be a minus
and then you may want to move it up so
it's sort of center in the button
there's our shop item list ui and to get
this working correctly into a list we
just need to add a grid um layout group
to the item scroll list and so we'll say
grid layout group and we'll say upper
left and select constraint will say
fixed column count and there's just
going to be one column pivot on our shop
item okay so you can see it's gone off
kind of killer here we need to set the
items to be pivoted to the top left
corner and so unfortunately i'm gonna
have to relay these out we'll select all
of our items we'll click onto the anchor
presets we'll hold down alt and click
the top left corner one and then let's
just reset our layout here okay so we've
um adjusted them we've got our item
scroll list and then we can start to put
in some padding and we'll do 32 on each
of the grid layout group which again is
on the item scroll list
object and let's just okay um these just
to see how these are going to lay out so
um now we can adjust the sort of spacing
and the cell size so if you want a bit
more of a gap between them you say it's
like 64 32 32 kind of works uh cell size
shouldn't matter too much um because
we're kind of controlling that all
through the sort of position of this uh
shop list item ui so you can see that
these are looking
quite good we can duplicate them and
because it's in a scroll box it'll go
kind of below the scroll view and we'll
be able to scroll down kind of in the
game i'm actually going to delete all
these go to our prefabs i'm going to
drag in this shop item list ui and i'm
going to make a prefab out of it and
then we're going to delete it from our
view i'm going to go over to the shop ui
controller which is the kind of top
level object and this is going to be
what sort of pops up when we access a
shop so it'll bring up the shop and we
can close the shop so this is the sort
of top level object and to this i'm
going to add a script i'm going to go to
my ui scripts folder i'm going to right
click create c-sharp script and we'll
call this the shopkeeper link
let's open this up in our um editor and
let's get started adding some variables
to this okay so we're going to need to
start
making fields for all the kind of ui
elements that we've just made so i'm
going to make a serialized field private
um and it's gonna be shop slot ui which
is going to be another script that we
put onto that shop slot that we just
made and so i'll say shop slot pre
tab and then let's actually make that so
in our ui scripts folder let's create
another script we'll call this the shop
slot ui this is the thing that we just
made with the buttons to add and remove
to the cart um we're gonna need another
one for uh we're gonna have to do
something quite similar for the shopping
cart section um but we'll get to that
kind of later on um we want a serialized
field or um a private button and this is
the uh
tab we'll need a one for the cell tab
and you see this is red here because we
need to import type using unity engine
ui we need to make sure we've got that
to kind of access the button and i'm
gonna make a header here i'm going to
call this the um shopping cart this will
be the shopping cart section i'm going
to do serialize field private mesh pro u
gui basket total text i'm going to
duplicate this a couple of times we're
gonna have the uh layer gold text as
well as the shot gold text and i have
another button reference so serialize
field private button and this is the uh
buy button on the shopping cart and then
we want a serialized field private
private text mesh pro u gui and this is
the buy button text so this is going to
change to say either buy or sell
depending which sort of tab we're in and
i'm going to make a new header we'll say
item preview action we'll do serialize
field private image and we'll do the um
item preview sprite serialize field
private text mesh pro u gui this is the
item preview name and we can copy this
and this is the item preview
description and we need a serialized
field private game object and this is
going to be our um item
game object uh item
list content panel and we'll duplicate
this and this will be our shopping panel
so let's go back to unity i'm gonna go
to our shop ui controller and to this we
can
add our shopkeeper display and we need
to hook all of these up so the shop slot
prefab that was the prefab that we just
um
made so if i go over to
prefabs shop slot uh shop item list ui
oh to that we need to add the shop slot
ui script that we've made that doesn't
do anything yet but that's fine uh we
can drag in our shop slot ui or the tabs
we'll do by tab and cell tab basket
total gold top gold and the buy sell
button the buy sell button text item
preview so we've got item sprite which
can go down there item name item
description and then we've got our item
list content panel which is this item
scroll list and then we've got the
shopping cart panel which is under
scroll view scroll bar view
viewport and we've got our shopping cart
list so that's our ui set up there i'm
just going to press save so let's make
the other prefab which is going to be
the um thing that we populate the
shopping cart with so so all this is
going to be and let's go to our shopping
cart list so that's this content panel
here i'm going to right click create
empty let's call this um dropping car
item and to that i'm just going to add
um some ui x for text mesh pro and we'll
put in
item name times 10. we'll stretch that
to fill kind of the available space it
has for our shopping cart item i'm gonna
again anchor it to the top left let's
make our um item kind of fill the
content panel here we will make this a
bit smaller and just give it a little
bit of padding and then on our shopping
cart on temp panel we need to do what we
did earlier so we need to make a um grid
layout group on this fixed column count
again is one we'll give it some padding
so 32 and spacing we'll do 32. so let's
anchor that to the sort of center left
actually and let's uh center it out on
there drag that in a bit so this is our
shopping cart item see as we've
duplicated then they've gone off the
panel uh we need to reduce the y on the
cell size about there gonna reduce the
padding on the top as well padding on
the left a bit there we go so we can add
multiple items to our basket now so
let's uh delete them make a prefab out
of our shopping cart item delete it from
the list let's make a new script then
called um c sharp script
shopping our item ui let's add that to
our shopping cart item prefab that we've
just made we'll jump back over to our
shopkeeper display um script and we're
going to do a serialized field private
shopping cart item ui we'll do shopping
cart item refab and we can hook that up
in the inspector as well so let's go
back to our shop ui controller drag in
our shopping cart item you want okay so
let's actually just get this displaying
and i think that'd be a good place to
end the video because it's gone on for
quite a little bit um so let's go over
to our project and i'm going to open up
our shopkeeper script and we can see
here that we've got um the i
interactable interface on it so when we
interact we can ask the ui manager to
display the shop system so um in our
interact function we can just uh let's
make a unity event so we'll do public
static unity
action and this is going to pass to the
shop panel it's going to pass the shop
system to our shop system it's going to
pass that in and it's also going to pass
in a player inventory player
inventory do we not have and it's going
to pass in the player inventory holder
and this is just going to be called um
on shot window requested so in our
interact we need to get the player
imagery component so i'm going to say
player
var player
inf is equal to interactor component
player inventory holder and then if our
player in variable is not equal to null
then we've got the player inventory
successfully we can say
on shop window requested and we're going
to invoke that by passing in our shop
system as well as the player inventory
we can end the interaction
um for now and then we'll do interact
successful is equal to true actually
let's get rid of that we don't need the
end interaction function in there and
then we can say else interact successful
was equal to false and then let's just
debug dot log error and player inventory
not found okay so back in unity on our
main canvas object i'm going to add a
kind of top level ui controller so
right click create c sharp script ui
controller and then let's add the ui
controller to our ui canvas and let's
open that up so in here on the um
on enable function we're going to
subscribe to
shopkeeper.on shop window requested and
let's do display
shop window which is um planing because
that's not a thing so let's implement
that so we've got a method that takes in
a shop system and a player inventory
let's rename this to shop system and
player inventory and then in on disable
let's
unsubscribe so on shop window requested
let's unsubscribe the display shop
window function let's take in a
serialized field shop private shop
keeper display and we'll say shop
display i'll call it shopkeeper display
yeah so the first thing all we're going
to do for now is we're going to open up
that panel so shopkeeper display dot set
active
game object sorry got set active do true
and then in awake let's make sure the
shopkeeper displays closed so
gameobject.setactive false so back in
unity shopui controller goes into there
so if we go over to our npcs we need to
add them to the interactable layer so
let's just choose um interactable and
we'll just say no this object only we
don't want to set the capsules as
interactable and let's add a capsule
colliders to the actual top level npcs
and remove them from capsule graphics so
if we hit play that should work go up
here we can hit e and that's going to
bring up our shop system uh window
that's gonna be it for this video in the
next video we're gonna work on looping
through the shop system and the player
inventory and displaying them
accordingly in this panel here and then
when we click the buttons on those um
shop ui panels we'll add them to the car
and we'll allow the player to actually
buy the item by clicking the buy item
button obviously all of this will update
and work very nicely if you'd like the
project files for this video and this
entire series so far they are available
on patreon which is
slash patreon.com i'd just like to take
a minute to thank all of my patrons on
screen now we can see the 10 000 xp tier
which is a sector sweep and i want to
thank all of the 4 000 xp tier members
as well if you need any help for this
video or any of my other videos feel
free to leave a comment below or head
over to the discord server which is
linked in the description and in the
meantime thanks for watching and i'll
see you in the next one bye
you